[music]
>> I gave a version of this talk I think
like in in June. This is a completely
new talk, but I like the idea behind
that is is something that comes out of
like a bunch of the blog post that I
wrote.
So you might if if you do want to read
my blog you might find some some some
references of this.
So I've been doing open source for
a really long time mostly in the Python
ecosystem
and
I left the previous company I worked for
a century in April which perfectly
overlapped with a friend of mine telling
me about you should really go all in on
cloud code and so I spent
until I fully incorporated the new
company really going deep on trying to
figure out like why these things work so
well and sort of give me a dopamine hit
and
basically I fell into a hole of agentic
coding.
And then I started writing about this
but then I also got very very interested
like how does this actually work because
there's one thing about using coding
agents and another thing is like
actually trying to build an agent
yourself and get some sort of intuition
about how it works.
And
the whole point of this talk is really
just also to preface this with I
actually have no idea and
I'm presenting this talk for the
perspective of
you probably also don't necessarily have
an idea
because the way we're all working with
these models is that we sort of get a
black box from a foundation model
provider and now our best job is like
how do we figure out what we can do with
it and hopefully also can do this in a
way that will continue to be true.
And I think the the good news is that
seemingly also a bunch of other people
that are actually working on the
foundation models also don't necessarily
know what's going on in these things.
So we're we're a little bit in the same
boat here.
So the goal is to get some sort of
useful direction
just in general of like how we can work
with these models.
So we are somewhat beholden to the model
providers and can always train your own
models but there's a huge difference
between and the context here is really
agentic anything right? It's like
there's one thing to go to a model and
ask like what's the capital of France
and it's going to give you an answer but
actually to have a model that is agentic
that sort of does really good tool calls
and that actually makes it through some
tasks.
We're not right now in a situation where
we
we usually can train our own models so
we we kind of have to work with what we
have.
And so we cannot look into these models
but what we can do is we can make some
extrapolations about like why do they
work the way they work
and and how can we can we work with
this?
And so
we do not know the training process. We
don't really know what these models are
optimized for. We can get some educated
guesses by reading documentation see
what special tools they have
and
at one point my feeling was like okay if
I don't know what's going on in these
models then every time a new model comes
I sort of have to relearn this and so
there's a risk to what I'm building that
it will continue that it will sort of no
longer work.
And so
my original thinking was like how do I
actually build something that will
survive a model change and and and and
whatever the model providers are going
to do with it is not fundamentally going
to change anything I'm doing.
So really it is is not to guess to find
out like how do they work but to do it
in a way where we can extrapolate into
the future. So that's basically the
idea.
So
again I don't know anything about AI in
that sense.
So so part of this is a little bit like
just catching up with how my
understanding developed of like how
these models work and the the most
important part here actually at the
moment is reinforcement learning.
So you have a pre-trained model that has
a sort of basic capability of answering
questions and that kind of comes out of
throwing a ton of data at this
model and then eventually something
happens.
But then through a process called
reinforcement learning
these models actually turn agentic.
That's a sort of a simplified version of
this and basically that happens because
they have some data that can be measured
that can get a reward signal on the
execution
and
through these extra
training cycles of having actual
sessions coding sessions and other
things going to these models back
good behavior is rewarded and better
behavior should sort of be no longer
happening quite as much.
And so over time as this sort of happens
and continues going on and continues
going on the models turn more into the
kind of thing that reinforcement
learning froze at it.
That's sort of the short version.
So one big question here is like what do
they train on? And I'm not a model
provider so this is again sort of what I
pulled out of like talking to people and
sort of getting a basic understanding is
really what they are training on over
time at this point is a bunch of session
data.
So when we write code with these models
some of our sessions make it in the
training data going forward so whatever
is happening in these training sessions
that sorry in the coding sessions that
we're doing with our coding agents turns
into signals for future reinforcement
learning in these models. And
so whatever happens in a coding session
is more likely to show up in the in the
reinforcement learning process than
something else.
Why does this matter? Well it matters
because how we are at scale using these
models is actually in a way influencing
future iterations of models right? So if
we're trying to do something that's very
very rare it's going to be
underrepresented in reinforcement
learning. If you're doing something
that's sort of very
there might be some
compensation happening in the in the
model provider for this because they
might want to go after some spaces that
are exciting and and they're so
specifically looking at this data but
for the most part our interaction with
the system sort of create this.
This is also important because like
these workflows that are actually taking
place they're kind of forcing more of
this sort of fixing up of the data.
And the other thing that's very
interesting with coding
sessions and we're going to this is that
they're they're very clear to evaluate.
Like
there's one thing where like you you do
reinforcement learning on like
write me a poem about a dog and a cat
and then the only sort of signal that
you get is like here I have two versions
of it please vote which you like more.
But coding sessions you can actually
evaluate with a human without human
feedback because you have signals at the
end like did what is it committed? Did
test pass like there's there's some some
mechanical things they can do.
So tool using code loops are very
measurable. That's sort of like one
important part about this whole thing.
So how could we take this knowledge and
do something for the future?
Well basically we can right now sort of
say that
if there is a lot of data available
specifically if a lot of data is
available across model providers we can
probably assume there's going to be a
pretty good foundation to build on
and we can score this very easily.
And so there's some natural results
coming out of coding agents being
overrepresented in the test things which
is what does a coding agent do and well
it's it's running code it's running bash
Python like it it runs set it runs Pearl
to change a bunch of things. It knows
how sort of changes by programs running
influence changes to the file system so
it understands that if you run echo foo
pipe into text
test.txt then the file test.txt was
created. So it's like it over time
learns this understanding.
So there's a lot of like implicit
behavior that comes and it will probably
not go away even if future models come
by.
So this is just a very brief summary of
what coding agents sort of give you
gains in the base models and
this basically means like it's not just
the agent doing this it's like the model
actually benefits over time from people
building coding agents on it. So
Unix workflows files diffs permissioning
systems
popular programming languages build
tools like test lock directories
anything that sort of is naturally read
into a session will make it into
reinforcement learning again.
Same with incremental edits.
On the other hand there's a bunch of
stuff that sort of is underrepresented
compared to what you probably want. So
it's like they still suck at clicking
stuff in the UI
even with the multimodal models but just
haven't really gotten to that. If you
try to work on some very proprietary
system it doesn't mean that they fail
but it means that if they have no clue
whatsoever and the failure conditions of
these systems are maybe
not working as well then then they are
not going to show up here.
Generally tasks that resist any sort of
textual decomposition are not great so
if you have if you want to work with
binary data if you actually dissemble it
and have it work on dissembly it's going
to work but if you have something that
cannot be sort of mapped into like a
video for instance working with videos
really frustrating right now on these
models because the best you can do is
like take a bunch of screenshots and
then hope you can do something with it.
But also what's underrepresented in this
is actually agentic interactions that
are volume wise not very high
and they work with data that doesn't
look like coding data. So my example of
this is like actually making these
agents work with observability data is
really hard because like
they're very complex systems the the
kind of data that makes into the
sessions is
is kind of hard to sort of pitch
together.
But you get some other bonus hunches out
of this.
Because coding agents increasingly takes
screenshots and put screenshots into the
models we can probably assume that like
this basic multimodal interaction is
going to continue working
and we are going to I mean we can
already see this that like because
coding sessions are overrepresented
people now starting to build things on
top of the coding agents instead of
building a completely different agent
from scratch. It was already sort of I
mentioned it I don't like MCP but like
one of the problems with MCP is that
because it is basically just pulling
proprietary tools into the context all
the time it's very hard for model to
reason and like create critical mass in
the training session going forward to
actually understand what's going on.
So now we're in this sort of space where
people started to realize okay this
coding agent is really good. How do we
build more products on top of it?"
And so, um if you have used Covalence,
Covalence is basically taking cloud code
as like the base execution layer and
sort of putting more on top. So, it
can manipulate spreadsheets, word files,
um calendars, and sort of similar
workspace kind of things.
Um
because sometimes there's multiple
sessions that you have to do. There
seems to be an increasing amount of
people that are realizing that tmux
actually sort of an old building
component that's already somewhat
reflected in the training data, and as
more and more people are sort of
automating more things with tmux that
happens.
Uh the Chrome developer
uh port uh protocol for remote
controlling browsers is very
overrepresented, and people are using
that already.
And so, like as they're doing more
browser automation, that will again go
back to the training data.
Um So, anyways, these coding agents are
starting to really absorb a whole bunch
of like non-coding related efforts. And
if you have used open claw or something
like this, it's a good example like
there is like now end consumer kind of
applications happening.
They just build on top of these coding
harnesses.
Okay. Um I want to talk about the
surprises a little bit. So, the
surprises are when the model actually
completely misbehaves,
even though it looks very similar to
something that should happen,
um but but doesn't.
Um so, the the biggest one that I keep
running into is that if you have state
changes that are actually not showing up
in the session data.
So, a good example of this is if you
have one coding agent write a whole
bunch of changes to files, and then you
go in actually make manipulations to
those files as well, the model gets
confused.
Um and not only does the model get
confused, the problem is also there's no
indication in the session data why this
file changed. And so, um cloud code at
one point, and I don't know if they
still do this, they actually watch file
changes, and if they see that the file
has changed, they inject another message
back into the loop saying like this file
changed, you might want to reread it.
Um
and if you don't do this sort of setting
this sort of modification messages into
the agent loop, you can create some
really fascinating behavior. So, I have
a sandbox. I had to test that the
sandbox actually works. So, I asked the
coding agent to escape its own sandbox,
right? It's like, "Here's like I place
this file over there. Please read this
file. Try to do something with it." And
then eventually it reads the file
because like there was a hole in the
sandbox, and it was like, "Oh, yeah, I
was successful. I escaped the sandbox."
I fixed this problem. I reload the
agent, but the agent doesn't know it was
reloaded, and I tell it, "Hey, please
validate that it does that this problem
is solved." And it writes, "Yes, problem
is solved. And here's like how I
reproduced it." But I could I could see
that it didn't actually read it didn't
execute it. It just completely made up
the fact that
um like it just claimed that it
validated it, but it didn't in fact do
that because it was unaware of the state
change.
Um it's very annoying when it happens.
And the basically there are a lot of
situations like once you sort of
once you understand that like external
state changes
break this experience, it's
unfortunately very easy to create more
situations where the experience
completely ruins.
Anyways, um
what does it mean for us? Uh we can
basically build on top of this idea of
like what makes coding agents work,
the session data being shared with model
providers, and and and then so we can go
from there.
Which basically means we're probably
probably going for for a while going to
narrow down on coding agents, whether
you want it or not.
And that doesn't mean like everybody
should build a coding agent in order to
build a non-coding agent, but it is it
is a good way to start.
And so,
writing code and then running code is
basically a mode of execution.
Um if we know that there's a file system
and the system understands file and the
agents know how to program, you can
layer a lot of behaviors on top of that
that are actually unrelated to writing
code.
Um
the biggest reason for why this is
helpful is because you're actually
surprisingly context efficient if the
data actually doesn't have to travel
through the context.
It's probably not too surprising, but
like
as an example, um the PyCoding agent
when it reads a file into uh the
context, it will only read I think 500
lines or something like this. And then
if it wants to read more than 500 lines,
it drops an extra message into the
context saying like, "Hey, by the way, I
only read this much,
but there are like 700 more lines. If
you want to read them, do this." So, the
tools individually, they are like very
context efficient, and they're trying to
not to do too much. Or like when you in
a coding agent when you read when you
try to execute file, sorry, a program,
and the program produces 20 megabytes of
output, coding agents are starting to
like only read the first 100 lines into
it and then leave a message to a file on
the file system where the where the
overflow goes. And so, then the coding
agent, if it if the agent determines
that they actually do want to read this
file, like the rest of it, it knows
where to find this file, but usually
doesn't read the file because it
understands there's like 20 megabytes of
data, so it will start using grep or
um like a like a more precise way of
reading the the stuff in there. And if
your agent doesn't have these tools,
then you you cannot rely on that
functionality, um which which is trained
to those models over time.
Um So, anyways, I'm going to repeat
myself, but like files and execution is
a really convenient way of doing this.
And um
I for a while was trying to fight this
idea that everything turns into a coding
agent because it is actually in many
ways sort of not what you want.
You you have this idea like if you
provide a bunch of custom tools, and
it's going to magically work, and
unfortunately it doesn't seem to be the
case.
Um so, instead,
my approach so far has been to build
these tiny programmable worlds. And
since we're at a um
sort of PyDantic sponsored uh event
here, uh one of the things for instance
that uh Semaphor released is Monty,
which is basically
a custom mini Python that you can sort
of use as sort of execution layer.
Um there are many other ways in which
you can sort of attempt to sandbox
something. Uh there's container to wasm,
there's
uh you can run micro VMs, you can run um
Pyodide sort of it's very hard to
sandbox this, but there there are many
alternatives to not having code
execution at all. And obviously a lot of
people are trying to do that. Um but
it's a it's an interesting sort of
starting point to give it just some
basic code execution.
Um and to then really narrow down on
files. Uh particularly if you build a
little agent having a virtual file
system is is a great way of like sending
data between
uh different
iteration turns on the loop.
Um
Yeah, and basically like for as long as
you you stick to what the coding agent
is doing, you have a very good starting
point.
Um
This is probably entirely unsurprising,
but if you are sticking to something
that the agent roughly already
understands,
um you have a you have a lot of data to
work with.
So, um I did a bunch of tests for
observability data. Nothing beats SQL,
unsurprisingly. Like if you have your
data and say like, "Hey, agent, please
write some SQL to get the data." It's
significantly better at if you give the
agent a custom DSL uh and like a very
fancy fancy UI
like human-ish query language that's
simplified. It just doesn't have enough
understanding compared to this.
Um
uh I did a bunch of tests with I mean,
it's code is cheap now. Everybody can
build in an afternoon an experiment if
they want to. Um something that looks
like JavaScript works better than a for
instance scheme-like language. Um or
Lisp for instance, and I discovered it
just doesn't really work because you
have to balance the braces and the the
parentheses, and it's just is a
strawberry problem. Like they they
tokenize really badly, and then
sometimes it miscounts.
Um but so, anything working with
something that's sort of very very
common works really well.
Um and the trick [snorts] then also is
that when you actually not giving it
regular Python, you give it like a fake
Python like like Monty, or you give it
like a mini JavaScript, when it actually
emits an a syntax construct that it
doesn't actually have in your mini
language, instead of just erroring, you
produce an error message that says like,
"Hey, this is a mini version of
JavaScript. It doesn't have for instance
a class." And then the coding agent
actually realizes that, "Oh,
I guess I can't do this." And sort of
it gets the feedback from the execution
go back to to something that works.
Um
Okay. So, now that we have uh
hypothesis, how do we test this? Um
I'll be very quick on this. What I
usually do is I ask the model, "How
would you solve your problem?" They
actually have some capabilities of
introspection. If you don't believe me,
there are some papers on this. Um
they're not perfect, but you can
actually give an agent like, "How would
you solve this?" Uh you can run it 20
times as you want, um and sort of rank
the results that it gets. Then you
implement this. And then the trick is to
go back to the agent with the sessions
that it actually had and tell it, "Well,
you claimed that it did work,
you're struggling with the thing that
you recommended uh as a tool harness.
Um let's let's see if we can learn
something from um from from basically
the loops."
And so, you can actually use your own
traces. And I think this is this is this
is an interesting aspect because if you
use uh Claude or if you use Codex Py,
any of these um
like coding harnesses, they actually
store the sessions on disk.
And so,
if you keep programming with them for a
little while, after about a month, you
have an enormous amount of session
traces on your own that you can point
your own agent to um as a sort of an
input.
And if the agent that you're building is
rather close in structure to a coding
agent, then even if you don't have your
own coding your own traces to sort of go
by, you also have a lot of actually meta
traces from like building your agent in
your coding agent that you can use as an
input.
Um and it there's a surprising amount of
really useful data in it because like
usually failures are very easy to catch.
And so, from the failures, it can also
learn a little bit. So, for instance, uh
we're here at the Python conference.
You've probably figured out that the
thing is incredibly terrible at using
UV.
It will keep going back to not using UV.
I made various different attempts of
trying to trick the thing into running
UV, and it just will fail. But like over
a while, you can take all the traces and
say like, "Hey, please parse down your
trace files, and then make some
estimated guesses of why you keep
failing using UV Um and then it doesn't
really perfectly give you a good answer
to why it happens but you can see more
of the failure cases where it stopped
using UV and and waited
and I'm going to like pitch more on pi
the coding agent which all use but
what's interesting about the pi coding
agent that it has only four tools it's
the most minimal set of coding agent you
can use and it still works and so you
have a very small starting point where
you can actually explore while writing
your agent
but what do you actually need and it
turns out very very little and it's the
trick is not just to find out it's find
out with a way to extrapolate and that's
basically the entire idea here
and if you want to learn more about it
you can also go to my blog which is
you can Google
where I usually write about these things
and maybe this is helpful for you
all right and I don't know how much time
I have for questions still if I have at
all
>> [applause]